

Ovande Furtado Jr Associate Professor

September 2023

Department of Kinesiology, California State University-Northridge

+1 818 677 5968

drfurtado.us

ovandef@csun.edu

**y** ofurtado

drfurtado

# About me —

Dr. Furtado received a B.A. in Physical Education from the Federal University of Parana, Curitiba, PR - Brazil. He earned his M.S. and Ph.D. degrees in Motor Behavior from the University of Pittsburgh, PA. Dr. Furtado's line of research focuses on two main areas: (1) validation of observational models in psychomotor assessment instruments and (2) the relationship between motor skill competence, perceived motor competence, physical activity levels, and body composition.

#### Education

1997

2009	Ph.D. Motor Behavior Pittsburgh, PA	Universityh of Pittsburgh
2004	M.S. Motor Behavior Pittsburgh, PA	Universityh of Pittsburgh

# **Professional Appointments**

**B.A Kinesiology** 

Curitiba, Brazil

· 2013-Present: Associate Professor, California State University-Northridge

Federal Univertsity of Paraná

- 2007-2013: Associate Professor, Eastern Illinois University
- 2006-2007: K-8 Physical Education Teacher, Falk School
- 2001-2005: Program Co-Director, Kinder Kinetics Movement Program

## Frequently Taught Courses (CSUN)

- · KIN 377 Motor Learning and Control
- KIN 477 Motor Development
- KIN 610 Quantitative Analysis of Research in Kinesiology

### Selected Publications

Azurdia, D., Acuña, S. M., Narasaki-Jara, M., Furtado Jr, O., & Jung, T. (2022). Effects of virtual reality-based aerobic exercise on perceptions of pain and fatigue in individuals with spinal cord injury. Games for Health Journal, 11(4), 236–241. https://doi.org/10.1089/g4h.2021.0151

Ladewig, I., Boell, I. B., Pereira, B. O., Spinelli, A. H., Franz, L. G., & Furtado Jr, O. (2019). The efficacy of using learning cues to teach children perform the backhand. Journal of Physical Education and Sports Management, 6(1). https://doi.org/10.15640/jpesm.v6nla6

Mazzardo, O., Fontana, F. E., Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2018). The relationship of movement skills with habitual and organized physical activity in seven and eight-year-old children. Pensar a Prática, 21(1), 135–146. https://doi.org/10.5216/rpp.v21i1.42360

Beals, T., Furtado Jr, O., & Fontana, F. E. (2018). Relative age effect and academic timing in american junior college baseball. Perceptual and Motor Skills, 125(1), 147–161. https://doi.org/10.1177/0031512517724260

Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2018). Expert-rater agreement and inter-/intrarater reliability for the Furtado-Gallagher Computerized Observational Movement Pattern Assessment System. Perceptual and Motor Skills, 125(3), 423-437. https://doi.org/10.1177/0031512518769205

Fontana, F. E., Furtado Jr, O., Mazzardo, O., Hong, D., & Campos, W. de. (2017). Anti-fat bias by professors teaching physical education majors. European Physical Education Review, 23(1), 127–138. https://doi.org/10.1177/1356336X16643304

Fontana, F. E., Furtado Jr, O., Marston, R., Mazzardo, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2013). Anti-fat bias among physical education teachers and majors. The Physical Educator, 70(1), 15–31.

Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2012). The reliability of classification decisions for the Furtado-Gallagher Computerized Observational Movement Pattern Assessment System—FG-COMPASS. Research Quarterly for Exercise and Sport, 83(3), 383–390. https://doi.org/10.1080/02701367.2012.10599872

Fontana, F. E., Mazzardo, O., Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2009). Whole and part practice: A meta-analysis. Perceptual and Motor Skills, 109(2), 517-530. https://doi.org/10.2466/pms.109.2.517-530

Fontana, F. E., Mazzardo, O., Mokgothu, C., Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2009). Influence of exercise intensity on the decision-making performance of experienced and inexperienced soccer players. Journal of Sport & Exercise Psychology, 31(2), 135–151.